Howard McClusky Collection
Howard McClusky Collection
1929-1990
Hiemstra, Roger.
6.5 linear ft.
Correspondence, writings, reports, speeches, notes, interviews, and other material by and about adult educator Howard McClusky.
2651138
Biographical History
Howard Yale McClusky (1900-1982) was a prolific and influential scholar of adult education. Born in Whitesboro, New York, he attended Park College in Parkville, Missouri and earned a PhD from the University of Chicago. He was a member of the School of Education faculty at the University of Michigan for 60 years, where he established the Graduate Program in Adult Community Education and was the administrator of the University's educational gerontology program.
McClusky was generous with his ideas and enthusiasm: in addition to his courses at the University of Michigan he was a visiting professor at ten universities, served on more than a hundred doctoral committees, published in more than fifty different journals and periodicals, served in an advisory capacity to dozens of organizations, and gave more than 430 presentations in 30 states and three countries. He helped found the Adult Education Association (serving as its first president) and the Commission of Professors of Adult Education, and was chief consultant to the W.K. Kellogg and C.S. Mott Foundations' efforts in the community council, community school, and citizen's council movements. Over the course of his career he made substantial contributions to many fields including mental health, public health, community education, community development, psychology, youth work, educational psychology, gerontology, and educational gerontology.
McClusky received numerous accolades over his career, including the Delbert Clark Adult Education Award (1956), University of Michigan Faculty's Distinguished Achievement Award (1958), Michigan Legislature Concurrent Resolution of Tribute (1969), Board of Regents' Citation (1975), Adult Education Association's Pioneer Award (1975), and State of Michigan Legislature's Award for Special Service. In 2002 he was inducted into the International Adult Education Hall of Fame. The McClusky Symposium, which continues McClusky's research exploration, is held annually at the National Adult Education Conference.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Howard McClusky Collection consists of correspondence, writings, reports, speeches, notes, and other material by and about adult educator Howard McClusky. The material was collected by Professor Roger Hiemstra, a colleague and protege of McClusky.
The material has been physically rearranged but retains Hiemstra's intellectual organization, folder titles, and descriptions. There is some overlap between series; researchers would be wise to review the entire inventory to ensure locating all relevant material.
Material About McClusky consists of bibliographies, articles, essays, letters, Hiemstra's research notes, and other material about McClusky. Correspondence contains letters and correspondence, some to and from McClusky and some about him.
McClusky's writings are collected by type in five series: Book chapters, Journal articles, Monographs, Speeches, and Writings, miscellaneous. Outside reports contains reports by various organizations on McClusky, or on topics related to his research interests.
Tapes contains 51 audiocassettes. Topics include speeches and lectures by McClusky, interviews with him and about him, and reminiscences of family, students, and colleagues about McClusky.
Miscellaneous includes bibliographies, lists of various kinds, biographical information, a few photographs, and assorted other material.
Arrangement of the Collection
The material has been physically rearranged but retains the collector's intellectual organization, folder titles, and descriptions. There is some overlap between series; researchers would be wise to review the entire inventory to ensure locating all relevant material.
Related Material
has extensive holdings in the field of adult education. Please refer to for a complete listing. For information about Syracuse University's complete range of adult education holdings, see the Alexander Charters Library of Resources for Educators of Adults website at http://scrc.syr.edu/charterslibrary.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Hiemstra, Roger.; McClusky, Howard Y.; Adult Education Association.; University of Michigan -- School of Education.; Adult education -- United States.; Community education -- United States.; Educational psychology.; Gerontology -- Study and teaching.; Life skills.; Older people -- Education.; Older people -- Psychology.; Adolescent psychology.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts (document genre); Monographs.; Papers (document genres); Photographs.; Proceedings.; Reports.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Roger Hiemstra, 2008.
Inventory
- About McClusky
  - AM-1: Radio Programs - The Awakening Community, October 8, 1939 - April 5, 1940; McClusky was the Director of the Programs (Box 1)
  - AM-2: 1969 Directory of Community Councils in Michigan, foreword dedicates the issue to McClusky (Box 1)
  - AM-3: McClusky's Academic Activities, undated (Box 1)
  - AM-4: McClusky’s membership to different organizations/institutions, undated (Box 1)
  - AM-5: Table 1: Type of Publication and Type of Authorship (of McClusky?), undated (Box 1)
  - AM-6: Letters to Dr. Tom parsons and others from Roger Hiemstra, 1979 (Box 1)
  - AM-7: "McClusky Talks on Aging" in: The University of Michigan School of Education, University Innovator, Vol. 11, No. 1, p.19, July 27, 1979 (Box 1)
  - AM-8: Letter to Arlon Elser, Program Director W. K. Kellogg Foundation, undated; includes request for support from Kellogg Foundation to work on McClusky's contributions to Adult Education (Box 1)
  - AM-9: Letter to Dr. Al Menlo, August 4, 1979; includes excerpts of McClusky's works (Box 1)
  - AM-12: A biographical essay about Howard Yale McClusky, undated (Box 1)
  - AM-13: Reference is made to McClusky about the meaning of “Educative" and "Human Psychology" by Prof. Allen Menlo, undated (Box 1)
  - AM-14: McClusky’s announcement of the establishment of a fund to partially support student participation in different academic activities. in Ace Reporter, Vol. 5 No.2, Oct. 1978 (Box 1)
  - AM-15: Description of McClusky by one of his 1924 students in a letter to the editor, September 1979 (Box 1)
  - AM-17: Code sheet, undated (Box 1)
  - AM-17.1: Working effectively with children and youth – meeting program, October 17, 1952 (Box 1)
  - AM-18: "The Power - Load - Margin Theory of Howard Y. McClusky as A Model of Teaching" / Dr. Keith Main, 1979 (Box 1)
  - AM-19: Community Colleges and Community Councils: Partners for Community Improvement? / Douglas Kelley, 1979; Two articles which refer to McClusky's work extensively (Box 1)
  - AM-20: Recollections and Reflections of Professors of Adult Education: Early 20th Century leaders and Pioneers in the Field / Joseph W. Jacques, 1973; McClusky is included as one of the pioneers (Box 1)
  - AM-23.1: Adult and Continuing Education Reporter, Vol. 6 Number 3: Special Issue, "A Tribute to Howard Yale McClusky", February 1980 (Box 1)
  - AM-24: Memorial Service for McClusky, October 23, 1982 (Box 1)
  - AM-25: Notes on McClusky by Roger Hiemstra in Address on: "Community Development and Education" by Howard Y. McClusky, May 1975 (Box 1)
  - AM-26: A brief tribute to McClusky upon his death in Adult and Continuing Education Reporter Vol. 9 Number 1, September 1982 (Box 1)
  - AM-27: Remarks on the Teaching of Howard McClusky / Carl Brahce, 1983? (Box 1)
  - AM-28: Letter from Helen McClusky to Roger on disposition of McClusky's books and materials, January 4, 1983 (Box 1)
  - AM-29: "Howard Y. McClusky, 1900-1982" / Lawrence S Berlin, Innovator, Vol. 14, No 3, December 1982 (Box 1)
  - AM-30: Adult Education in Ann Arbor: A Candid Look at the Adult and Continuing Education Faculty at the University of Michigan, Howard McClusky p.41, 1979 (Box 1)
  - AM-31: Classes taught through extension service, undated (Box 1)
  - AM-32: Announcing the death of McClusky, August 25, 1982 (Box 1)
  - AM-33: Community Adult Education from 1938-1953 - its first 15 years (Box 1)
  - AM-35: Education for Elderly by 2000 in Dowagiac MI Daily News, April 5, 1979 (Box 1)
  - AM-36: Education for the Aging, University of Michigan, March 23, 1979; article reviewing Dr. McClusky's conception of education and gerontology by the year 2000 (Box 1)
  - AM-38: "University of Michigan Professor will give commencement address," The Bryan Times, May 17, 1957 (Box 1)
  - AM-40: Documents regarding Milan Community efforts with some inputs by Prof. McClusky, January, 1946 (Box 1)
  - AM-99: A Dynamic Approach to Participation in Community Development, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - CO-1: Letter from William E. Becker A comment on McClusky's interview on "An Education for All Seasons", March 26, 1980 (Box 1)
  - CO-2: Letter from Doug Kelley on Reference letter from McClusky, December 18, 1980 (Box 1)
  - CO-3: An invitation to speak to Directors of Community Education, March 12, 1968 (Box 1)
  - CO-4: A memorandum from Robert A Luke to Dr. McClusky re: Affiliation of the Adult Education Association with the National Education Association and other organizations (Box 1)
  - CO-5: A circular from Coolie Verner to Professors of Adult Education, re: adult education growing rapidly but lacking specific direction or logical progress (Box 1)
  - CO-6: Letters to Mrs. McClusky on Howard's death, 1982 (Box 1)
  - CO-7: Letter from George W. Sample to McClusky on the Juvenile Question, April 21, 1936 (Box 1)
  - CO-8: Letters to and from McClusky concerning "Education for Community Leadership", August, 1944 (Box 1)
  - CO-9: Correspondence on Discussion Groups as a Channel of Information, 1947 (Box 1)
  - CO-10: Letter from Alex Sobel, August 17, 1957; includes latest copy of the Council Reporter, request for materials on Community Council history, directions, programs and their effectiveness (Box 1)
  - CO-11: Some correspondence on reports of the Symposiums at the National Institute on Education and the War, August/September, 1942 (Box 1)
  - CO-12: Letter to Dr. Don C. Charles, Iowa State University Professor, Department of Psychology, regarding submission of a book chapter or an article, January 4, 1979 (Box 1)
  - CO-13: Letters from Roger on bibliography of McClusky, July 19 and July 20, 1979 (Box 1)
  - CO-14: Letter from Dr. Francis A. Kornegay to McClusky expressing his enjoyment in reading the latter's article, June 26, 1979 (Box 1)
  - CO-15: Letter from D. Barry Lumsden, Editor, Educational Gerontology appointing McClusky as Life Honorary Editor of the journal, June 10, 1979 (Box 1)
  - CO-16: Correspondence between McClusky and Roger Hiemstra, 1979 (Box 1)
  - CO-18: Letter to McClusky from Roger Hiemstra enclosing a list of doctoral students McClusky chaired, 1979? (Box 1)
  - CO-19: Correspondence from the Canadian Education Association requesting McClusky for the publication of the latter's article in their book, December 4, 1956 (Box 1)
  - CO-20: Letter to Boyd enclosing a memorandum on Educational Research, July 7, 1962 (Box 1)
  - CO-21: A memorandum from Reports Committee to McClusky on "Adult Education as a Field of Professional Study", February 12, 1962 (Box 1)
  - CO-22: A Memorandum to Dr. Olson, Dean, School of Education, containing a report on sabbatical leaves, second semester, 1962-63 (Box 1)
  - CO-22.1: Correspondence and later notes on work with the Michigan Credit Union League, 1954 (Box 1)
  - CO-23: Correspondence with various people on different topics and issues, 1951 (Box 1)
  - CO-23.1: Correspondence pertaining to the 1980 Adult Education Handbook series (Box 1)
  - CO-23.2: Letter to William Griffith from McClusky on AEA publications, July 9, 1982 (Box 1)
  - CO-24: Correspondence enclosing Notes for Report to Bruce Fund Committee of which McClusky was a member, September 6, 1950 (Box 2)
  - CO-25: A report of the Adult Education Conference which McClusky attended, June 26, 1951 (Box 2)
  - CO-26: Correspondence from Mark Starr to McClusky regarding Workers' Education, February 18, 1952 (Box 2)
  - CO-27: Copies of letters of different people to McClusky on their appointment to different positions in the AEA plus some writings regarding the organization found in one file, 1952 (Box 2)
  - CO-29: Letter to Wilbur J. Cohen sending him a supplement to the Biographical material, March 29, 1978 (Box 2)
  - CO-30: Letter to John Hatfield enclosing a copy of selected professional biographical items (resume), August 24, 1977 (Box 2)
  - CO-31: Letter from Frank J. Misplou confirming Dr. McClusky's presentation of the Life-long Learning seminar at the New England Gerontology Centre, July 17-19, 1978; December 21, 1977 (Box 2)
  - CO-32: Letter from Patrick R. Penland to McClusky enclosing an executive summary and the final report on Self-Planned Learning, December 5, 1979 (Box 2)
  - CO-33: Letter from Roger Hiemstra enclosing a copy of the article Hiemstra sent to Lifelong Learning, March 6, 1980 (Box 2)
  - CO-34: Copy of a letter from Burton W. Kreitlow to William S. Griffith and copied to McClusky, May 31, 1979 (Box 2)
  - CO-35: Letter from William Griffith enclosed with a copy of the revised manuscript of the volume Alan Knox was editing, July 3, 1979 (Box 2)
  - CO-36: Letters from and to William S. Griffith, 1979 (Box 2)
  - CO-37: Letter from William S. Griffith concerning edition of books, July 25, 1979 (Box 2)
  - CO-38: Letter from Huey B. Long enclosing a copy of a review of a book entitled Changing Approaches to Studying Adult Education, July 15, 1980 (Box 2)
  - CO-39: Letter from J. Lin Compton on Tenure Review, September 22, 1980 (Box 2)
  - CO-40: 1981 KIHCOA Session at this November National Adult Education Conference in St. Louis, July 17, 1980 (Box 2)
  - CO-41: Copy of a letter from Carl I. Brahce to Murray Jackson on Dr. McClusky’s proposed appointment as chair of the Educational Gerontology Program and as a member of the Educational Gerontology faculty for the 1973-74 Academic Year, August 24, 1973 (Box 2)
  - CO-42: Letter to Dr. K. Warner Schaie reporting on the Adult Ed Association of the USA conference and the National Mini White House Conference held in November 1980; both he and McClusky attended, December 23, 1980 (Box 2)
  - CO-46: Copy of a letter from William S. Griffith to Dr. Edgar J. Boone enclosing the first two chapters of the Handbook Volume with some comments, March 19, 1978 (Box 2)
  - CO-47: Copy of a letter from William Griffith to Edgar J. Boone enclosing chapter VI "Basic Education English as a Second Language " with some comments, March 20, 1978 (Box 2)
  - CO-50: Copy of a letter from William S. Griffith to Dr. Allan B. Moore on publishing the Handbook series, February 25, 1978 (Box 2)
  - CO-51: copy of letter from William S. Griffith to Dr. Linda S. Hartsock regarding expenses for the preparation of each volume of the Handbook series, February 24, 1978 (Box 2)
  - CO-54: Letters from and to Charles B. Wood regarding trends in Adult Education, 1973 (Box 2)
  - CO-55: Letter to Professor Jerold W. Apps, Chairman, Commission of Professors of Adult Education reporting that the meeting for the Part-Time Teachers was a decisive success, March 13, 1972 (Box 2)
  - CO-56: Letter from Andrew Hendrickson expressing their appreciation to McClusky for his acceptance to deliver an opening address at their institute on Development of Education Programs for Older Persons, March 10, 1972 (Box 2)
  - CO-58: Letters from the Nebraska Educational Television Council for Higher Education, Inc., personnel regarding a supplemental lesson, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - CO-62: Letter from W. Fred Totten concerning an article for the special issue of the Phi Delta Kappan, April 29, 1972 (Box 2)
  - CO-65: Letter from W. A. Buckmann enclosing a list of board members and a list of institutional members, July 11, 1978 (Box 2)
  - CO-66: Letter from Mary P. O'Brien on presentation "Coping with Changes in the Later Years", August 10, 1978; includes draft of program (Box 2)
  - CO-67: Letter from Jacques O. Lebel, Commission Chair ensuring McClusky that plans for him to participate at an AEA Conference session on the 1981 WHCOA were set, October 15, 1980 (Box 2)
  - CO-68: Letter to J. Lin Compton responding to his note of May 15, and enclosing some documents describing the mission of Compton’s Community Task Force, August 22, 1980 (Box 2)
  - CO-69: Letters from and to Dr. Roger Hiemstra regarding McClusky's visit to Lincoln for a NETCHE Program, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - CO-71: Letters from and to Dr. Roger Hiemstra regarding information about expansion of Roger's Department of Adult Education, February, 1972 (Box 2)
  - CO-72: Letter from Mary L. Reiss appreciating Dr. McClusky’s acceptance to speak at the HEW Region V Staff Development Workshop, August 29, 1972 (Box 2)
  - CO-80: A note to Bill Griffith on preliminary observations concerning the task of the Professors' Publication Committee, January 1, 1975 (Box 2)
  - CO-81: Letter to Dr. Alton P. Hadlock regarding Adult Education Program Planning, undated (Box 2)
  - CO-85: Correspondence from Ray Manty, listing suggestions to the UP, March 1, 1944 (Box 2)
  - CO-86: Correspondence to McClusky regarding recreation programs in schools, April 18, 1944 (Box 2)
  - CO-87: A memo to McClusky on the future of the Committee on Education for Aging, AEA, November 1, 1951 (Box 2)
  - CO-88: Correspondence to Dr. E. L. Kirkpatrick regarding the American Youth Commission, December, 1941 (Box 2)
  - CO-91: Correspondence with Mrs. Samuel Geraci of Northville Community Council regarding Community Service, November 16, 1964 (Box 2)
  - CO-92: Correspondence from C. R. Carhohan regarding the development activities of Mount Pleasant Town Hall Michigan and related documents, October 19, 1946 (Box 2)
  - CO-94: Correspondence from Alvin Zander regarding the School of Education, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, May 24, 1948 (Box 2)
  - CO-97: Letter from the President of the AMCA College, Chicago, Lake Geneva, July 16, 1930 (Box 2)
  - CO-100: Letter from Alan B. Knoll regarding a report on relevance to Adult Education of the College Textbook Educational Psychology by Lee Conback, second edition, dated 1962, August 4, 1965 (Box 2)
  - CO-101: A memo to Robert C. Clark regarding the proposed Iowa Dissemination Project, August 13, 1940 (Box 2)
  - CO-102: Letter to Senator Dick Clark on the Huron College Project in Intergenerational Education, September 17, 1976 (Box 2)
  - CO-103: Letter to Ms. Carole Tice giving her an abbreviated preview of some of the major outcomes of the evaluation of the TLC Mote Module Project, June 26, 1980 (Box 2)
  - CO-104: Letter from Charles E. Scholl Jr. enclosing McClusky's paper on "Adult Education for Today’s World,", August 17, 1951 (Box 2)
  - CO-105: Correspondence pertaining to McClusky’s initial employment at the University of Michigan (Box 2)
- Book chapters
  - BC-1: An eclectic introduction to child development, undated (Box 2)
  - BC-2: Adult Education as a Field of Professional Study, January 22, 1962 (Box 2)
  - BC-5: The Adult as Learner, reprinted from: Stanley E. Seashore and Robert J. McNeill (eds.) Management of the Urban Crisis, 1971 (Box 2)
  - BC-6: The Outlook of Youth in a World at War in Sidonic M. Gruerberg (ed) The Family in a World at War, 1942 (Box 2)
  - BC-8: The Teachers and the Small Community University of Nebraska Press, 1948 (Box 2)
  - BC-11: Psychology and Learning, undated (Box 2)
  - BC-13: The Community of Generations: A Goal and a Context for the Education of Persons in the later years, August, 1975 (Box 2)
- Journal articles
  - JA-1: An experimental comparison of reading the original and digest versions of an article, Journal of Educational Psychology, November, 1940 (Box 2)
  - JA-2: Reactions of teachers to the teaching situation – a study of job satisfaction, Howard McClusky and Floyd Strayer, The School Review, October, 1940 (Box 2)
  - JA-2.1: A philosophy of work experience, Progressive Education, February, 1942 (Box 2)
  - JA-3: The Status of Youth in Our Culture, reprinted from Education, December, 1955 (Box 2)
  - JA-4: Age and Youth: A Partnership (Youth as a source of energy if there is planning and laborious constructive effort), May 10, 1941 (Box 2)
  - JA-5: Block Organization for Health Education, reprinted from American Journal of Public Health, Vol. 34, No. 6, June, 1944 (Box 2)
  - JA-6: Community Influences and Adult Learning, in Adult Education, Vol. VIII, No.2, Winter 1958 (Box 2)
  - JA-7: The Psychology of Adults, for Review of Educational Research, undated (Box 2)
  - JA-8: Mental Health in Schools and Colleges, pre-print of chapter in Review of Educational Research, December 1949 (Box 2)
  - JA-9: What's Ahead in Education? reprint from Pi Lambda Theta Journal Vol. XXXI, No.4, pp. 199-202, Summer,1953 (Box 2)
  - JA-10: Adult Education about Education, reprint of Chapter VI from Review of Educational Research, co-authored by Herbert Hamlin, June, 1953 (Box 2)
  - JA-11: The adult education program. Back cover in the Michigan Alumnus, March 9, 1944 (Box 3)
  - JA-12: General Education and Work Experience, reprinted from Review of Educational Research, October, 1944 (Box 3)
  - JA-13: The Future of Camping, in The Camping Magazine, February, 1937 (Box 3)
  - JA-15: The Normal Child and Adolescent, reprinted from Review of Educational Research, December, 1943 (Box 3)
  - JA-16: Shall I go to High School? reprinted from Farm Journal and Farmer’s Wife, September 1943 (Box 3)
  - JA-17: An Age for Greatness: The Secondary School at War, reprinted from Michigan Educational Journal, January 1943 (Box 3)
  - JA-18: Planning for Rural Youth, reprinted from the Journal of Educational Sociology Vol. 15, No. 9, May 1942 (Box 3)
  - JA-19: The Common Problems and Possibilities of National Agencies Concerned with Community Organization in Community Councils, in Action Vol. 1, No. 4, May 1941 (Box 3)
  - JA-20: The School in the Community, reprinted from the North Central Association Quarterly, Vol. XV, No.4, April, 1941 (Box 3)
  - JA-22: A Modified Form of the True-False Test, reprinted from the Journal of Educational Research, Vol. 14, pp. 213-224, co-authored with Francis D. Curtis, October, 1926 (Box 3)
  - JA-24: Psychology and Learning, in the Review of Educational Research, Vol. 35, P. 191-200, June, 1965 (Box 3)
  - JA-25: The Psychology of Adults, reprinted from Review of Educational Research, Vol. XXIX, No.3, co-authored with Gale Jensen, June 1959 (Box 3)
  - JA-27: The Adult as Lifelong Learner: Some implications for instruction in higher education, in Educare Journal Vol. 5, Spring 1978 (Box 3)
  - JA-28: A Study of Community Leaders Perceptions, in Adult Education Volume XV Number 4, Summer 1965 (Box 3)
  - JA-29: A Modified form of the True-False Test, in General Science Quarterly, undated (Box 3)
  - JA-29.1: Howard Yale McClusky, Adult Education Professor and Statesman, in Lifelong Learning, October, 1980; undated; also includes correspondence between Roger Hiemstra and others concerning McClusky (Box 3)
  - JA-29.2: The contributions of Howard Yale McClusky to an evolving discipline of Educational Gerontology, by Roger Hiemstra, 1981 (Box 3)
  - JA-30: Adult Education for Citizenship, reprinted from Review of Educational Research, October, 1947 (Box 3)
  - JA-31: The Occupational Adjustment of the Youth, reprinted from the National Business Education Quarterly, undated (Box 3)